Register of the Edgar Jacob Fisher papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Edgar Jacob Fisher papers
1888-1933
79037
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
The collection relates to Robert College and other American schools in Turkey and elsewhere in the Near East, social and political conditions in Turkey, and ethnic minorities in Turkey. It consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, reports, student essays, and printed matter.
Fisher, Edgar Jacob, 1885-1968.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into 2 series: Turkey subject file and Robert College file
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Edgar J. Fisher collection, Ohio State University Libraries
Edgar J. Fisher archive, Fine Arts Library, Harvard University
Mary Mills Patrick papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Ernest W. Riggs papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Edgar Jacob Fisher was born in 1885. He earned his PhD from Columbia University in 1911, where he authored New Jersey as a Royal Province, 1738 to 1766 (New York: Columbia University). As a proponent of international education, Fisher worked as a professor of social studies and dean of Robert College in Constantinople (Istanbul) from 1917 to 1933. In 1924, Fisher was briefly dismissed by the Turkish Minister of Education for allegedly speaking unfavorably about the government to a group of tourists, only to be rehired in 1925. In his time in Turkey, Fisher wrote a number of short articles that appeared in professional journals and The New York Times about the state of affairs during the first World War and international education. He also worked as the assistant director of the Institute of International Education. He died in 1968.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection relates to Robert College and other American schools in Turkey and elsewhere in the Near East, social and political conditions in Turkey, and ethnic minorities in Turkey. It consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, reports, student essays, and printed matter.
Although mainly focused on events surrounding American schools in the Near East, the collection includes a number of clippings, professional journal articles, writings, and correspondence about Turkey's history, culture, and ethnic minorities, as well as the burgeoning Nationalist Movement, Treaties of Sèvres and Lausanne, formation of the Republic, and Kemalist reforms; all of which appear in the Turkey subject file. Some of the folder titles used in this part of the collection are from the records' creator, hence archaic forms of place names.
In an effort to standardize curricula, secure funding, and encourage cooperation among the heads of American schools in the Near East, Fisher worked on the Advisory Committee on Education of the Committee of Cooperation on American Education in the Near East, the correspondence and reports of which appear in the Robert College file. Also included in this file is correspondence regarding Fisher's expulsion from Robert College by the Minister of Education, and student research papers on Turkey's ethnic minorities, including Bulgarians, Persians, Gypsies, Greeks, and Armenians.
Robert College (Istanbul); Education--Middle East.; Education--Turkey.; Minorities--Turkey.
- Turkey subject file, 1888-1933 (Box 1-2)
  Clippings, correspondence, printed matter, and published and unpublished writings by others, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General, 1888-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Angora (Ankara), 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Armistice of Mudros, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Atatürk, Mustafa Kemal, 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Constantinople (Istanbul), 1920-1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Constitution, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Education, public and private, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ethnic minorities, 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Evictions and deportations, Harput, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gallipoli Campaign, circa 1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Goldstein, Adolph, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Government, 1910-1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Harems, 1890; 1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - History, 1890-1931 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Literature, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Music and dance, 1917, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Religion, 1891-1923 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Smyrna (Izmir), 1922 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Treaties, general, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Treaty of Lausanne, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - World War I, 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - World War I (contd.), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Young Men's Christian Association of Constantinople, 1921-1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Robert College file, 1917-1932; Boxes 2-3 (Box 2-3)
  Includes correspondence, reports, charts, and other writings relating to Fisher's activities as dean of Robert College, professor of social studies, and participant in the Advisory Committee on Education of the Committee of Cooperation on American Education in the Near East. Also includes a group of essays written by students on Turkey's ethnic minorities. Maintained in original order, with correspondence arranged chronologically
  - Circulating correspondence, 1923-1932 (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
    - 1923 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence regarding expulsion, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
    - 1924 July-August (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1924 September (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - 1924 October-November (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "A Brief Survey of the Development of Robert College Since the War,", 1930 October (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Advisory Committee on Education of the Committee of Cooperation on American Education in the Near East, 1917-1921 (Box 2-3)
    - Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 12-17)
      - 1920
        - March-July (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
        - October-November (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - 1921
        - January (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - April (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Report and research on American colleges in the Near East, 1921 and undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Research on enrollment and budget at selected American universities, 1920 June (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Chart of admission requirements for New York state colleges and universities, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Charts prepared by Fisher, 1920 June (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Scope and Content note
      Includes comparative analysis of American schools in the Near East, admission requirements and enrollment figures for different disciplines
    - Expense account statements, 1920 July (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Near East education questionnaire, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - Revisions, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Essays by students, 1928-1931 (Box 3, Folder 3-9)
      Includes essays written on the topic of Turkey's ethnic minorities for an assignment titled "A Descriptive Sample of Human Society"